Ayush Kalla

akalla@stevens.edu | 6465778976 | https://github.com/akalla123 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/ayushkalla/

PROFILE SUMMARY

Data Scientist with skills and experience in building custom statistical models especially in the credit risk and revenue space. Proficient in the field of statistics, specifically Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence. Other interests include building Computer Vision and Time-Series Models, Data Visualization and Sales & Profit Forecasting.

WORK EXPERIENCE

MATRIX ANALYTICS CORPORATION

Ridgefield Park, New Jersey, U.S.

Data Scientist

Jun 2020 -Present

Jun 2019 - April 2020

- Delivered Model Risk Management Dashboards to track model performance post deployment for a lending client.
- Working on building code, enhanced templates and defining a best practice for one of the key milestones of XAI model development process of Credit risk management models of MATRIX.
- Built AI based time-series forecasting models to perform demand forecasting of inventory. Used various approaches of AI Long short-term memory (LSTM), Spline regression, ARIMA, Holt-Winter and multi dimensional macroeconomic model adjusted predictions for a retail company client.
- Working on developing a deep learning solution for a retail client to determine the composition of products using images. Used algorithms such as Convolutional Neural Network and Masked RCNN.
- Built budget, cashflow and monthly sales and purchase monitoring Tableau dashboards for retail clients.

Data Scientist Intern

Built suite of AI based revenue and balance models for one of the major banking client.

- Automated the task of Exploratory Data Analysis by writing a Python Script to perform analysis on any given dataset.
- Developed front-end forms for clients to get user-input and run Machine Learning models for the client using JavaScript.
- Built Dashboards using IoT data from sensors for a retail client.
- Automated the task of data processing by performing Exclusion Analysis by preparing a general template to work for any type of incoming data.

Central Drug Research Institute

Lucknow, India

Sep 2017 - Dec 2017

Research Intern

- Analyzed over 30 research papers and data sources to gather data on the spread of Parkinson's Disease. Visualized various trends in the spread of Parkinson's Disease across the Globe using Tableau.
- Determined various factors directly or indirectly affecting the disease.

EDUCATION

STEVENS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

Hoboken, New Jersey, U.S.

M.S. in Information Systems

Aug 2018 - May 2020

Relevant Coursework: Web Mining, Knowledge Discovery in Databases, Marketing Analytics

Projects:

- Human Trafficking Knowledge Graph A knowledge graph generating project that helped identify over 100 cases of Human Trafficking around NYC. Judged as the best solution for the competition.
- Hate Comment Detector A flask powered website to automatically filter hate comments from Twitter and Live News using Logistic Regression algorithm.

UNIVERSITY OF MUMBAI

Mumbai, India

B.Tech. in Information Technology

Aug 2014 - May 2018

Relevant Coursework: Web Development, Advanced Database Management Systems, Object Oriented Programming, Data Mining and Business Intelligence

Projects:

AutoPlay - A Machine Learning model to predict the outcome of a cricket game beforehand, based on the past records and performances.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, R, SQL, JavaScript

Tools: Scikit-Learn, NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Tableau, MS Excel, OpenCV, Keras, Tensorflow

Database Management Systems: MySQL, SQLite3 Internet Technologies: Flask, HTML5, CSS, XML, jQuery